<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://obi-wan-shinobi.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://obi-wan-shinobi.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2023-10-20T14:30:18+00:00</updated><id>https://obi-wan-shinobi.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Magical Wonders and Moving Castles - A Journey into ‘Howl’s Moving Castle’</title><link href="https://obi-wan-shinobi.github.io/blog/2021/howls-moving-castle/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Magical Wonders and Moving Castles - A Journey into ‘Howl’s Moving Castle’"/><published>2021-01-12T13:56:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-12T13:56:00+00:00</updated><id>https://obi-wan-shinobi.github.io/blog/2021/howls-moving-castle</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://obi-wan-shinobi.github.io/blog/2021/howls-moving-castle/"><![CDATA[<p>Ghibli brings us another masterpiece in the form of Howl’s Moving Castle which, in my opinion, is widely underrated and misunderstood. Its important to observe how Studio Ghibli gets more and more intricate with all the films that it produces and it clearly shows how Miyazaki matures as a director as he makes Howl’s Moving Castle and how that is reflected in him making a film about adulthood.</p> <p>Howl’s Moving Castle, at first watch, seems like a fairy tale, which is what most people focus on albeit failing to notice the complexity and intertwining of different layers of the movie. As with all other Miyazaki films, there are a lot of layers to Howl’s moving castle. The fairy tale layer, mythology layer, environmental layer and more. The most important being that over time as Miyazaki matures as a director, his films that were already complex, become even more complex and granular. There are entire story arcs that happen within a moment that contribute to the character development. And with every re-watch, we can spot newer and newer things owing to the scenes that are so tightly packed that Miyazaki probably just wanted people watching it again and again. For instance you can see that Sophie appears different in every scene throughout the film depending on the context or the war that is developing in the background that suddenly pounces off in the latter half of the film. One can observe how Miyazaki is reusing his own symbols from his previous films in forms of metaphors that he has already introduced in a different context. Like the umbrella from Totoro. That is how the Miyazaki theory takes root in the modern standing where symbolism is at utmost importance that Miyazaki uses to convey a message. When we watch animation, we expect to see things that are out of the ordinary and Miyazaki’s unique gift is to infuse the ordinary with magical qualities.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/posts/howls-moving-castle/cleaning-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/posts/howls-moving-castle/cleaning-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/posts/howls-moving-castle/cleaning-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/howls-moving-castle/cleaning.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Even the most boring of the daily chores, cleaning, is given these treat- ments. There is an awe inspiring attention to details and a sense of wonder in those details is what makes those scenes that much more transporting. Of course, the great thing about this film is that if you don’t want, you don’t have to pay attention to any of these details and go with the story because it’s based so well on the characters that you can go through the story as one of them and get your own emotional breakthroughs.</p> <p>In a press conference, Miyazaki said, <em>”While always saying that I have to or want to make films for children, in reality I often forget about them. That’s how I end up creating films like Porco Rosso and Howl’s Moving Castle”</em>. And it is interesting in the sense that this film is about adulthood more than other Miyazaki films which have some sort of coming-of-age story going on whether its mythological or practical or growing up, trying to find solutions to the problems that your parents’ generation has created or growing up by finding a place in society and the modern world. And after all these <em>coming-of-age</em> stories, this is a film that stars people who are actively trying to avoid adulthood.</p> <p>Sohpie is shown to have a lovely outlook on life at the beginning of the film. She doesn’t want to live her life making hats in the backroom, but her experience of life is that it’s still better in there that out somewhere and that’s a mutual sentiment which all introverts can empathize with. When Sophie gets her ”curse”, it seems quite a relief for her which is not usually how curses work. She is really quick to embrace what has happened and it means that she can skip the adulting thing entirely.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/posts/howls-moving-castle/relief-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/posts/howls-moving-castle/relief-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/posts/howls-moving-castle/relief-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/howls-moving-castle/relief.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Then we have Howl who is permanently stuck in adolescence. He loves the power that comes with growing up but not the responsibilities. Through- out the film he tries to be everything for everyone while being afraid of losing control of his power and not being loved.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/posts/howls-moving-castle/adolesence-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/posts/howls-moving-castle/adolesence-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/posts/howls-moving-castle/adolesence-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/howls-moving-castle/adolesence.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>And his emotional breakdown reveals some of these things that his character is struggling with.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/posts/howls-moving-castle/breakdown-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/posts/howls-moving-castle/breakdown-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/posts/howls-moving-castle/breakdown-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/howls-moving-castle/breakdown.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Then there’s Marco who we barely know but can deduce that he’s the kind who has had to grow up too quickly for some reason. His actual job is to pretend being an adult but in the later half of the film we learned that what he needs is belonging and family.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/posts/howls-moving-castle/acting-old-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/posts/howls-moving-castle/acting-old-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/posts/howls-moving-castle/acting-old-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/howls-moving-castle/acting-old.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Calcifer is the most ancient and mythological thing in the film who has ties to the Hindu God Agni. Despite his roots, he’s actually dealing with the same problems that the other characters are but in a more metaphorical sense. His question is, <em>”What happens if I change? Can I change while remaining the same person that I am now? If I change, do I die?”</em>.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/posts/howls-moving-castle/ancient-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/posts/howls-moving-castle/ancient-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/posts/howls-moving-castle/ancient-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/howls-moving-castle/ancient.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>The short blink-and-you’ll-miss-it story line is of the dog that has exactly one decision point in the entire film. It involves coming out of dependency and stand for something which is why he joins the adventurers.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/posts/howls-moving-castle/blink-and-miss-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/posts/howls-moving-castle/blink-and-miss-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/posts/howls-moving-castle/blink-and-miss-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/howls-moving-castle/blink-and-miss.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>The final character is the house and people often overlook this but the house itself is a character which changes throughout the film. The question for the castle is the same as Calcifer, ”What happens if I keep changing? Can I be put together again if I fall apart?”. And this latter question poses an undertone in which the castle symbolizes Japan. And throughout the film, the castle grows and changes and it suffers but it survives all of the changes, and these were the changes needed for it to grow and become more of the house that we can all live in.</p> <p>All the characters dealing with the difference in What I show to the outside world vs How I am really feeling? is the Japanese separation of the outward facing facade that people put on for society’s sake. Even the house has its context dependent output faces.</p> <p>The question is ”Why are these people trying to avoid being adults?”. Well, its because of what adults are like. In the film, adults are greedy, egoistic, manipulative, toxic. Looking at the adults that Sophie sees around her, her colleagues who are super shallow and gossip about having a better life but not doing anything about it. Her sister, whose life revolves around looking pretty and pleasing men in return for attention. Her mother who has a constant competition about being the best. And if that is what being an adult is like for Sophie, its no wonder that you skip it. Then there’s Howl’s adult, Soloman. A corrupt mother figure. A king who’s an idiot father figure. The Witch of the waste is only interested in magic because of the greed. And all the other wizards that did what they were taught to do and ended up losing their humanity completely. The point that the film makes is that even though all adults are horrible, all these coping mechanisms that the characters use to avoid adulthood do not work. Escapism is not the solution. Whatever magic the characters use, the truth is under there. So they have to figure out how to become adults in a way that they stay true to themselves. Miyazaki wants the characters to live their true lives and find their true spirits. So the path that the characters realize is of finding their true selves and story of the characters is to help each other find their own true selves. The story fed is, How, who lives in the delusion that he can solve everything with careful maneuvering. And of other Miyazaki male heros, his learning curve is much steeper. Miyazaki’s bottom line is that no war is worth going into. You cannot solve war by winning it.</p> <p>The ending is one of the weirder Miyazaki endings because by the end, everything resolves suddenly. But if you watch the film close enough and see the internal logic, the entire story was a set up to that ending. Miyazaki achieves this with a combination of fairy tale rules and therapy rules. In fairy tales, you find the point of the main plot and you solve it and the kingdom gets magically restored. In therapy, you get down to the core of your problem, crack it, get your breakthrough moment and the bigger the change is, the bigger is the ripple effect on your life. And that is what happens at the end of the film. People find their true hearts, literally. What is misplaced is replaced (the scarecrow), literally. And the violence stops because the need for the thing that was substituted for violence was fulfilled and there’s no more need for violence.</p> <p>But the real statement is how the choice is not between becoming a horrible adult or not growing up at all. The resolution comes from the characters when they learn to define for themselves what adulthood is, what family is, what is worth making a stand for and what is making effort for and that’s the kind of adult that Miyazaki would like you to be.</p> <h3 id="related">Related</h3> <p>I was inspired to write this based on <a href="https://www.followthemoonrabbit.com/howls-moving-castle-people-dont-want-to-be-adults/">Adam Dobay’s</a> lecture on Howl’s Moving Castle. If you enjoy Ghibli content, I highly recommend you check out his blog <a href="https://www.followthemoonrabbit.com/">Follow the Moon Rabbit</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="movie-blogs"/><category term="ghibli"/><category term="blogs"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Unlock the magic and wonder of Studio Ghibli's 'Howl's Moving Castle' in this captivating blog journey through the enchanting realms of the film.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Grave of the fireflies - an emotional masterpiece</title><link href="https://obi-wan-shinobi.github.io/blog/2020/grave-of-fireflies/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Grave of the fireflies - an emotional masterpiece"/><published>2020-11-18T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-18T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://obi-wan-shinobi.github.io/blog/2020/grave-of-fireflies</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://obi-wan-shinobi.github.io/blog/2020/grave-of-fireflies/"><![CDATA[<p>Being in the western or the eastern part of the world has never stopped fans from taking a moment to appreciate exceptional content and those who love the Japanese culture of anime most certainly will get their heads out at the mere mention of the name “Studio Ghibli”. Studio Ghibli has been, by far, the most influential animation studio that has brought about the revolution in anime industry in Japan. With all the movies that the studio has produced over the years, be it Totoro or Spirited Away, there is not a single feature film that hasn’t stood out uniquely with a background of its own. The brilliant mind of Hayao Miyazaki has led to powerful storylines such as Howl’s Moving Castle and Princess Mononoke which manage to extensively present the recurring theme that Miyazaki has always preached. Over a career spanning five decades, Miyazaki seems to have had a strong and almost unbreakable bond with three notions that are prominent throughout his movies i.e. wind, women and revolution. The theme of Ghibli strongly resonates with these ideas along with a lingering emphasis on pacifism. With the big deal that Miyazaki is, we’re here to talk about the second most important person in the Studio Ghibli franchise and a lifelong friend of Miyazaki, Isao Takahata and his beautiful creation that is <em>“Hotaru no haka”</em> or more commonly known as <em>“Grave of the fireflies”</em>.</p> <p>Takahata has been a crucial peg in the Ghibli machine over the years and having produced masterpieces like Pom Poko, it’s hard to argue otherwise.</p> <p>Centering on two kids who try to survive post world war II Japan, there’s not a lot of movies that can be boiled down as easily as this one compared to other works that Ghibli has blessed us with. For any viewer, two things are prominent- First, the animation is excellent and the story is well written and second, it’s not exactly a joyful, happy film that will leave you with a warm feeling in your heart. It’s just sad. Prohibitively, unremittingly sad. And it’s not exactly the ideology you have in mind when a Ghibli film can be expressed so simply. But the more you immerse yourself in the story, it stops being a movie and becomes more of an unending duty that you wish will go the other way in every moment. However satisfying it feels to understand a movie this way, it forecloses our ability to understand the movie further in all its depressing glory.</p> <p>Grave of the fireflies is an emotional experience so powerful that it forces a rethinking of animation. The essential component that makes the film so interesting is the raw density of ideas that it wants to get across in such a short runtime. The movie is centered on the drama of its two main characters that give the viewer the modest impression that it’s exclusively about these kids and the struggles that they face in the World War II era of Japan. Having grown up in the same era, Takahata instills a horror that wars realize in a society that is burdened with famine, loss and disease. That it might press upon the viewers to ponder over the actions of each character. And I might point out that the film, although seems to be invested in exploring the two characters, doesn’t have a monolithic idea that it centers on. Rather, it really explores a variety of thematic and emotional tensions and pushes the audience to grapple with a bunch of conflicting and unsettling ideas. The most obvious idea that the film plays with is that beauty and childlike innocence are fragile and short-lived. This idea is broadcasted by the title of the movie “Grave of the fireflies” which refers to this scene from the movie where Seita and Setsuko get a bunch of fireflies for their cave.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/posts/grave-of-fireflies/cave-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/posts/grave-of-fireflies/cave-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/posts/grave-of-fireflies/cave-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/grave-of-fireflies/cave.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>However beautiful, the fireflies are dead by the morning indicating the fact that audience has to come to terms with. Beauty is fragile and delicate. In the beginning of the movie, the film makes an emphasis on how Seita makes a big deal out of not losing his mom’s ring, giving the audience the impression that this ring is going to mean something. But after the only scene, the ring is never spoken of again. This symbolizes the changing importance of things that always makes us prioritize our needs. Instead of this ring, the symbol of permanence and stability is associated with the fruit drops that Seita gives to Setsuko. Like the fireflies, these candies are able to provide one brief, joyful experience to a kid who doesn’t have much left and like the fireflies, they are ephemeral. And these ideas are connected to the characters themselves with Seita and Setsuko’s temporary and blissful childhood.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/posts/grave-of-fireflies/piano-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/posts/grave-of-fireflies/piano-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/posts/grave-of-fireflies/piano-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/grave-of-fireflies/piano.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Why does all this happen? Why is the world like this? And here is another idea that presents itself into the film. Concentrating on the death of Setsuko, we’re left wondering who is responsible for it. The answer, simply enough, is everybody. The choices that people make ripple down into the dying state of the society. The Americans decide to go to war after the Japanese decide to bomb Pearl Harbor. When their mother dies, the kids move in with their aunt who treats them like second class citizens. Because of this, Seita decides they should live off on their own, and then the kids starve. The farmer decides that he can’t afford to sell them anymore food. After Seita decides to steal, the farmer beats him up brutally. The cop shows him some compassion but offers him just a glass of water. The doctor just suggests that Setsuko needs some food and decides nothing to do about it. The point of the movie is not to vandalize these characters but instead the audience is presented with contradictory facts that they have to settle with. First, the society is struggling and the people are doing as much as they can to help each other. Second, the decision that every person takes results in death of a child. Everybody can be blamed but most people did nothing wrong. The film continues providing the audiences with many thematic tensions throughout the films where we observe that things the audience primarily desire end up being awful choices. For instance,</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/posts/grave-of-fireflies/leaving-home-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/posts/grave-of-fireflies/leaving-home-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/posts/grave-of-fireflies/leaving-home-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/grave-of-fireflies/leaving-home.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Looking at the awful way that the aunt treats the protagonists, it’s natural to want one of the two things to happen, either the kids can change their situation and make it livable or the kids can escape the situation and find a better place for themselves. But neither of those gestures can really amount to anything. The kids can’t change the situation in World War II era Japan and how could they? Their attempt to leave their aunt’s house only results in starvation and despair which is indicated by the farmer in the middle of the movie where he asks Seito to go back to her. From Seito and Setsuko’s perspective, the system is totally broken. There is not enough food to go around and the woman who’s supposed to take care of them is cruel and selfish. But the possibility of surviving after leaving that broken system was none. This is where the film presents the audience with another conflicting idea. The things that the protagonists face are heart wrenching and tragic. But the sheer possibility of the same sequence occurring with anyone else is forgotten. When you present the film like this by isolating its theme and putting the story in right order, it starts to get a bit overwhelming. It seems that the movie just wants to get at a bunch of interesting feelings but doesn’t really care about having an intellectual through-line. But there is a connective tissue that links the various ideas in the movie together. It’s normal in most movies to be able to blame the main conflict on one entity, either the antagonist or the protagonist. But Grave of the Fireflies says that everybody is to blame. And as opposed to Miyazaki’s theme of revolution, where the character who’s in a bad system changes the system, Isao Takahata emphasizes on idea that sometimes we need to stay in the broken systems. Sometimes, we have two choices- remain in a bad place or die trying to escape it. It’s normal to expect a story to frame its main characters as the only things of importance to imply that we are focusing on them for good reason but Grave of the fireflies explains that there are countless tragedies that we could have talked about.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/posts/grave-of-fireflies/food-shelter-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/posts/grave-of-fireflies/food-shelter-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/posts/grave-of-fireflies/food-shelter-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/grave-of-fireflies/food-shelter.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>And there’s something deeply incidental about the facts talking about this one. The very first line of the movie has Seita telling us the date he died. And since he’s alone when he dies, we can extrapolate that Setsuko’s dead too.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/posts/grave-of-fireflies/first-line-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/posts/grave-of-fireflies/first-line-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/posts/grave-of-fireflies/first-line-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/grave-of-fireflies/first-line.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>From then on we just follow Seita’s ghost as he watches his and his sister’s final days unfold. It’s hard to overstate the importance of this framing device to the movie as a whole. It informs every second of my experience with it and it makes me feel detached from what’s going on with our characters. There are many scenes in the movie which could have had very different emotional impacts. The sad moment where Seita tries to find food for his sister could feel very different from the comfortable one where they eat rice. The oppressive moment where their aunt is mistreating them could feel very different from the liberating one, where they pack up and leave. But the framing makes sure they don’t feel radically different. When we see them eating food, we recall the moment where Seita gives his aunt his mother’s silk and see Seita’s ghost recoil at how awful that decision was. When I see them go to the woods, there’s no part of me that can relate to a feeling of childhood wonder and adventure because it’s so obviously a mistake. The constant sense of despair that the movie invokes is the opposite of intimacy. Seita and Setsuko experience a million emotions in this movie. Joy, excitement, fear, oppression. But I don’t feel those things. I feed bad and impudent the entire time. And because I can never locate myself in the headspace of the characters, I am pushed away from them. There is one scene that brings out this separation than any other. The kids that discover Seito and Setsuko’s shelter out in the woods.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/posts/grave-of-fireflies/cave-2-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/posts/grave-of-fireflies/cave-2-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/posts/grave-of-fireflies/cave-2-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/grave-of-fireflies/cave-2.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>This scene serves no purpose as far as the plot is concerned but enforces our position as an audience. We are these kids. Like them, we’re just a bunch of people who stumbled upon a tragedy. We have the ability to look at what’s happening and say that our lives aren’t so bad after all. We can go there, feel bad for a second and then, most importantly, leave. The film challenges the act of watching as it does in many other places and problematizes our ability to enter the text and understand what it means in any constructive way. After all, we’re not Seita or Setsuko. Their lives and deaths are not for us to inhabit. All we can be is observers on margin, looking on, from very far away.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="movie-blogs"/><category term="ghibli"/><category term="blogs"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Unearthing the Emotional Depths of 'Grave of the Fireflies'.]]></summary></entry></feed>